本节我想给大家展示另一种密钥交换的方法
In this module I wanna show you another
approach to key exchange based on the
(口误：module->segment)
用于公约加密的概念。再帮大家提示一下有关设定
concept of public key encryption. So again
just to remind you of the settings, we
通常，我们有朋友Alice和Bob，他们要交换密钥K
have our friends Alice and Bob as usual,
and they're both to exchange a secret key
窃听者能看到他们之间发送的信息
K. The eavesdropper gets to see the
messages they send to one another, but
但即便如此，他也不应该学到任何关于
双方交换的密钥K的信息
even though he shouldn't learn anything
about the key K that, that they exchanged.
通常在本章里，我们只看对窃听的安全性
And as usual in this module we're only
going to be looking at eavesdropping
也就是说，我们不允许攻击者去修改数据
security. That is we don't allow the
attacker to tamper with data or to mount
或实施其他形式的主动攻击。那么提醒一下大家，
在本章的早些时候
any other form of active attack. So, just
to remind you, earlier in this module we
我们看了一个低效的基于普通分组密码的机制
saw an inefficient mechanism based on
generic block ciphers. In the previous
上一节我们看了Diffie-Hellman密钥交换机制
segment we saw the Diffie-Hellman key
exchange mechanism which has an
它在参与者必做工作和攻击者必做工作之间
exponential gap between the work that the
participants have to do versus the work
有一道指数级鸿沟。事实上Diffie-Hellman协议
that the attacker has to do. And in fact
this Diffie-Hellman protocol is used all
在网络中频繁应用。本节我想给大家看
over the web very frequently. In this
segment I want to show you, a different
一个基于公钥加密的不同的方法。
那么什么是公钥加密？
approach based on public key encryption.
So, what is public encryption? So just as
就像对称加密一样，有一个加密算法
in the case of symmetric encryption, there's an encryption algorithm and a
和解密算法。不过这里的加密算法有一个密钥
decryption algorithm. However, here the
encryption algorithm is given one key,
我们把它叫做公钥，我们说这个公钥
which we're going to call a public key.
Let's call this the public key that
属于Bob。而解密算法有一个不同的密钥
belongs to Bob. And the decryption algorithm is given a different key, we'll
我们叫它私钥，它也属于Bob。这两个密钥
call it a secret key. That also belongs to
Bob. So these two keys are sometimes
优势叫做密钥对。密钥对的一半是公钥
called a key pair. One half of the pair is
the public key and the other half of the
另一半是私钥。通常，你加密这个信息的方法是
pair is the secret key. Now the way you
encrypt this as usual, a message would
加密算法会产生一个密文
come in, the encryption algorithm would
generate a cipher text, that is the
是使用公钥加密的。然后当密文
encryption of this message using the given
public key. And then when the cipher text
交给解密算法解密时，解密算法会输出
is given to the decryption algorithm, the
decryption algorithm basically outputs the
对应的明文。如我所说，PK叫做公钥
corresponding, message. So, as I said, PK
is called the public key and SK is called
SK叫做私钥。更为精确地，公钥加密是什么意思？
the secret key. So more precisely, what is
public encryption? Well, public encryption
公钥加密实际上由3个算法组成：G, E和D。
is actually made up of three algorithms,
G, E, and D. Algorithm G is what's called
算法G叫做密钥生成算法。当你运行算法G时，
它会产生两个密钥
a key generation algorithm. When you run
algorithm G, it will output two keys, the
分别是公钥和密钥。给定明文中的公钥
public key and the secret key. The
encryption algorithm basically, given the
加密算法会输出对应的密文
public key in the message, will output the
corresponding cipher text. And the
给定密文中的私钥，解密算法会输出明文
decryption algorithm, given the secret key
in the cipher text, will output the
或输出符号⊥，如果发送错误。通常
message or it will output bottom if an
error occurred. And as usual we have the
我们有一致性，即密钥生成算法输出的
usual consistency properties that say that
for any public key and secret key that
公钥和私钥，如果我们使用公钥加密明文
could have been output by the key generation
algorithm if we encrypt the message using
然后用私钥解密，我们可以获得最初的明文
the public key and then decrypt using the
secret key we should get the original
现在，安全的公钥系统是什么意思？
message back. Now, what does it mean for a
public key system to be secure? Well, we
我们使用与之前用过的语义安全同样的概念
use the same concept of semantic security
that we used before, except the game is now
但游戏有点不同。我来解释一下，如何定义
a little bit different. So let me
explain, how we define semantic security
公钥系统的语义安全。这里，挑战者运行
for a public key system. So here, the
challenger is gonna run the key generation
密钥生成算法，来产生一对公钥和私钥
algorithm to generate a public key and a
secret key pair, and he's gonna give the
他会把公钥给攻击者。挑战者对私钥进行保密
public key to the adversary. The
challenger keeps the secret key to
与之前一样，攻击者会输出两个等长度的明文M0和M1
himself. What the adversary will do is he
will output two equal length messages M0 and
然后挑战者会给攻击者M0或M1的加密结果
M1 as before and then the challenger will
give him the encryption of M0 or M1. As
通常我们定义两个实验：实验0和实验1
usual we define two experiments: experiment
zero and experiment one. In experiment
在实验0中，攻击者得到M0的加密结果
zero the adversary is given the encryption
of M0. In experiment one the adversary is
在实验1中，攻击者得到M1的加密结果，
然后攻击者的目标是
given the encryption of M1 and then the
adversary's goal is to guess which
猜他得到的是哪个明文的加密结果。他获得的是M0的加密？
encryption he was given. Was he given the
encryption of M0 or was he given
还是获得了M1的加密？我们把他的猜测作为实验0
encryption of M1. And we refer to his
guess as the output of experiment zero or
或实验1的输出。我想强调的一点是
experiment one. One thing I want to
emphasize is that in the case of public
在公钥加密中，没有必要赋予攻击者以实施
encryption there's no need to give the
attacker the ability to mount a chosen
选择明文攻击的能力。为什么？在对称密钥系统中
plaintext attack. Why is that? Well in
the case of a symmetric key system, the
攻击者必须请求他选择的明文的加密
attacker had to request the encryption of
messages of his choice. In the case of a
而在公钥系统中，攻击者拥有公钥，所以
public key system, the attacker has the
public key and therefore he can by
他可以自己加密任何他想加密的明文
himself, encrypt for himself any message
that he wants. He doesn't need the
他不需要挑战者的帮助，来计算他选择的明文的加密。因此
challenger's help to create encryptions of
messages of his choice. And as a result,
在公钥的设定中，选择明文攻击是与生俱来的
in a public key setting, a chosen
plaintext attack is inherent. There's no
没有理由给攻击者多余的能力去实施选择明文攻击
reason to give the attacker extra power to
mount a chosen plaintexts attack. And
这也是我们为什么不讨论选择明文的询问
that's why we never discussed chosen
plaintext queries in the context of
在定义公钥系统的语义安全时。现在我们定义了这个游戏
defining semantic security for public key
systems. Now that we defined the game
我们说，一个公钥系统(G,E,D)是语义安全的
we're going to say that a public key system
(G,E,D) is semantically secure if
如果攻击者无法区分实验0和实验1
basically the attacker cannot distinguish
experiment zero from experiment one. In
换句话说，在实验0中攻击者输出1的概率
other words, the adversary's probability
of outputting one in experiment zero is
和在实验1中他输出1的概率差不多相同
about the same as his probability of
outputting one in experiment one. So again,
那么攻击者也不能区分他得到的是M0的加密
the attacker can't tell whether he was
given the encryption of M0 or the
或是M1的加密。现在我们理解了什么是公钥加密
encryption of M1. Now that we understand
what a public key encryption is let's see
我们来看如何使用它来建立一个共享密钥。
这里是我们的朋友Alice和Bob
how to use it to establish a shared
secret. See here are our friends Alice and
Alice开始时会为她自己产生一个随机公钥、密钥对
Bob. Alice will start off by generating a
random public key secret key pair for
使用密钥生成算法。然后她把公钥PK
herself using the key generation
algorithm. And then she's going to send to
发送给Bob。她还跟Bob说，这个信息来自Alice
Bob the public key PK. And she also says,
hey this message is from Alice. What Bob
Bob会产生一个随机的128位值X
will do is he will generate a random 128
bit value X and he will send back to Alice
他会回复Alice，说：这个信息来自Bob。他还会
返回用Alice的公钥加密的X
saying hey this message is from Bob and he
will send back the encryption of X under
Alice会收到这个密文，她会解密它
Alice's public key. Alice will receive
this cipher text, she will decrypt it
使用她的私钥，解密结果会给她值X
using her secret key and that will give
her the value X and now this value X can
现在，X可以被用来作为双方共享的密钥
be used basically as a shared secret
between the two of them. I wanna emphasize
我想强调，这个协议和我们上节看到的Diffie-Hellman协议
that this protocol is very different from
the Diffie-Hellman protocol that we saw in
很不相同，这里双方必须有先后地通信
the last segment in the sense that here
the parties have to take turns, In the
Bob不能发送他的信息，直到他收到了Alice的信息
sense that Bob cannot send his message
until he receives the message from Alice.
换句话说，Bob不能用Alice的公钥加密X
In other words, Bob cannot encrypt X to
Alice's public key until he receives the
直到他收到了Alice的公钥。但在Diffie-Hellman协议中
public key from Alice. In the
Diffie-Hellman protocol however the two
双方可以在任何时候发送他们的信息
parties could send their messages at
arbitrary times and there was no ordering
没有对信息的发送顺序的强制要求。因此
我们有这个很好的Diffie-Hellman协议的应用
enforced on those messages. As a result we
had this nice application of
例如，每个人都可以在Facebook上发布他们的信息
Diffie-Hellman, where, everybody could
post their messages to Facebook, for
然后只看Facebook页面，任何一对用户
example. And then just by looking at
Facebook profiles, any pair would already
都可以共享一个密钥，不需要任何附加通信
have a shared key, without any need for
additional communication. Here, this is
而这里不是这样，即使每个人在Facebook上发布公钥
not quite true, even if everybody posts
their public key to Facebook, there would
依然需要先发送信息，才能建立共享密钥
still be a need to send this message
before a shared key can be established. So
现在我们理解了这个协议。第一个我们需要问的问题是
now that we understand protocol the first
question we need to ask is why is this
为什么这个协议是安全的？目前我们只考虑对窃听的安全
protocol secure. And as usual we're only
gonna look at eavesdropping security. So
在这个协议中，攻击者看到这个公钥和X的用公钥的加密
in this protocol the attacker gets to see
the public key and the encryption of X
他想得到这个值X
under the public key and what he wants to
get is basically this value X. Now we know
现在我们知道，我们使用的这个公钥系统是语义安全的
that the system the public key system that
we used is semantically secure, what that
这意味着攻击者不能区分X的加密
means is that the attacker cannot
distinguish the encryption of X, From the
和某个随机信息的加密。换句话说，仅仅给X的加密
encryption of something random. In other
words, just given encryption of X, the
攻击者无法分辨明文是X，还是某个其他的
从明文空间M里选取的随机信息
attacker can't tell whether the plain text
is X or just some random junk that was
因为这点，这说明只看协议里的信息
chosen from M, And because of that, that
basically says that just by looking at
在攻击者来看，X的值是无法与
messages in this protocol, the value of X
is indistinguishable in the attacker's
从明文空间M里选取的随机元素相区分的，
因此，X可以被用作双方的会话密钥
view from a random element in M and as a
result, X can be used as a session key
它仅仅是一个随机值，攻击者不能猜到
between the two parties. It's just a
random value which the attacker cannot
除非尝试M里的所有可能值
actually guess other than by trying all
possible values in M. Then I should say
那么我应该说，这两个分布是不可区分的
that showing that these two distributions
are indistinguishable follows directly from
这是直接由语义安全得到的结果，事实上容易证明
semantic security and in fact it's a
simple exercise to show that if the
如果攻击者可以区分这两个分布
attacker could distinguish this
distribution from that distribution then
那么攻击者也可以破解语义安全
the attacker could also break semantic
security. And as usual even though this
通常，即使这个协议对窃听是安全的，对抗中间人攻击时
protocol is secure against eavesdropping,
it's completely insecure against the
它也是完全不安全的。那么我们来看一个简单的中间人攻击
man-in-the-middle attack. So let's see a
simple man in the middle attack. Well so
那么这里我们有，Alice产生她的公钥、密钥对
here we have Alice generating her public
key secret key pair. At the same time the
同时中间人也产生他自己的公钥、密钥对
man in the middle is also going to
generate his own public key secret key
现在当Alice发送她的公钥给Bob时
pair. And now when Alice sends her public
key over to Bob, the man in the middle
中间人会截获这个公钥，然后他会对Bob说：
这个信息来自Alice
will intercept that and instead he'll say
yeah this is a message from Alice, but
Alice的公钥是PK'。现在Bob接收了这个信息
Alice's public key is PK prime. So now
Bob receives this message, he thinks he
他认为他获得了从Alice发来的信息，他要回复，
他会选择他的随机数X
got a message from Alice, what he'll send
back is, well he's going to choose his
然后他会返回X的用PK'的加密
random X, and he'll send back the
encryption of X under PK prime. The man in
中间人会截获这个信息，他会用其他信息来代替它
the middle is going to intercept this
message, and he's going to replace it with
他的目标是确保这个密钥交换成功
something else. So, his goal is to make
sure that the key exchange succeeds, in
换句话说，Alice认为她获得了来自Bob的信息
other words Alice thinks that she got a
message from Bob, and yet the man in the
同时中间人应该能确切地知道，交换的密钥是什么
middle should know exactly what the
exchanged secret is. So what should the man in
那么这里，中间人应该发送什么给Alice呢？
我们把这个密文记为C
the middle send to Alice in this case? So
yeah let's call the cipher text C. What
中间人会解密这个密文C，使用他自己的私钥
the man in the middle will do is he will
decrypt the cipher text C using his own
这样中间人会得知X。然后
secret key that will reveal X to the man
in the middle. And then he's going to go
他会继续加密X，用Alice的公钥，把加密后的值发回给Alice
ahead and encrypt X under Alice's public
key, send the value back to Alice. Alice
Alice会获得这个她关心的X，她完成了与Bob的密钥交换
will obtain this X and as far as she's
concerned, she just did a key exchange
双方都学到了值X，不过当然，问题是
with Bob, where both of them learned the
value X, but the problem of course is that
中间人也知道了这个值X。所以这个协议是完全不安全的
the man in the middle also knows the value
X. So this protocol becomes completely
一旦中间人可以修改从Alice到Bob的信息
insecure once the man in the middle can
tamper with messages from Alice to Bob and
或是从Bob到Alice的。所以我们必须对这个协议
再做一些事情，确保它的安全
from Bob to Alice. So again we have to do something to this protocol to make it secure and
我们将看到怎么办，这要等到两周后
we're gonna see how to do that, actually,
in two weeks after we introduce digital
我们引入数字签名后再看。现在我们已经给大家
看了公钥加密蕴涵着密钥交换的安全性
signatures. So now that I've show you that
public encryption implies key exchange
从对抗窃听的角度而言。
下一个问题是，我们如何组建公钥加密系统？
security against eavesdropping. The next
question is how do we construct public key
实际上这些机制一般都依赖于
encryption systems? And it turns out that
these constructions generally rely on
数论和某些代数，就像Diffie-Hellman协议
number theory and some algebra, and just
like the Diffie-Hellman protocol relied on
依赖与某些代数一样。那么在我们看这些协议的更多细节前
some algebra. And so before we go into
these protocols in more detail what I'd
我想先回避一下。下一章我们要看
like to do is kind of take a quick detour.
In the next module we're going to look at
相关的数论背景。我们花一章来讲数论
the relevant number theory background.
We'll just do one module on this and then
然后回到密码学，讨论这些公钥机制，
和更多的密钥交换的机制
come back and talk about these public key
constructions and more constructions for
那么本章完结。作为进一步阅读
key exchange. So this is the end of this
module. And as further reading, I just
我只想指出这篇论文，他证明了事实上
wanted to point to this paper that shows
if in fact all we do is rely on symmetric
如果我们只依赖于对称密码和哈希函数，那么
Merkle谜题对于密钥交换而言是最优的选择
ciphers and hash functions then
Merkle puzzles are optimal for key
事实上我们不能获得比平方鸿沟更好的结果
exchange and in fact we cannot achieve
more than a quadratic gap as long as we
只要我们把这些原型当作黑盒。那么这证明了
treat the primitives we're given as a
black box. So basically this shows that a
平方鸿沟是最好的可能结果，我还想指出另一篇论文
quadratic gap is the best possible and
also I wanted to point to another paper
这篇论文总结了一些我们讨论过的密钥交换机制
that kind of summarizes some of these key
exchange mechanisms that we talked about,
使用公钥密码学的密钥交换，
和使用Diffie-Hellman的密钥交换
key exchange using public key cryptography
and key exchange using Diffie-Hellman. You
大家可以看一下这篇论文，它会给大家一点展望
can take a look at this paper and it kind
of will give you a look ahead into what's
如何让这些密钥交换协议对中间人攻击是安全的
coming and how to make these key exchange
protocols secure against man in the middle
而不仅仅是能对抗窃听。那么本章完结
and not just secure against eavesdropping.
Okay so that's the end of this module and
下一章我们先避开密码学，简单看一下
in the next module we'll take a brief
detour and do a kind of a brief overview
代数和数论
of algebra and number theory.